<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!--
Part of the Fluid Corpus Manipulation Project (http://www.flucoma.org/)
Copyright University of Huddersfield.
Licensed under the BSD-3 License.
See license.md file in the project root for full license information.
This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme
(grant agreement No 725899).
-->
<!-- DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE ... YOU WILL LOSE YOUR WORK -->
<c74object name='fluid.transients~' category='FluidCorpusManipulation'>
	<digest>Realtime Transient Modeller and Extractor</digest>
	<description>Separate transients from a signal.</description>
  <discussion>
    <h4><openfilelink filename="Fluid Corpus Manipulation Toolkit.maxpat">Open the Overview Patch</openfilelink></h4>
            <p>This implements a &quot;de-clicking&quot; algorithm based on the assumption that a transient is a sample or series of samples that are anomalous when compared to surrounding samples. It creates a model of the time series of samples, so that when a given sample doesn't fit the model (its &quot;error&quot; or anomalous-ness goes above <m>threshfwd</m>) it is determined to be a transient. The series of samples determined to be a transient will continue until the error goes below <m>threshback</m>, indicating that the samples are again more in-line with the model.</p>
        <p>The algorithm then estimates what should have happened during the transient period if the signal had followed its non-anomalous path, and resynthesises this estimate to create the residual output. The transient output is <m>input signal - residual signal</m>, such that the summed output of the object (<m>transients + residual</m>) can null-sum with the input.</p>
        <blockquote>
        <dl class="docutils">
        <dt>The algorithm will take an audio in, and will divide it in two outputs:</dt>
        <dd><ul class="first last simple">
        <li>the transients, estimated from the signal and extracted from it</li>
        <li>the residual of the material with the transients replaced with an estimate.</li>
        </ul>
        </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>The algorithm implemented is from chapter 5 of &quot;Digital Audio Restoration&quot; by Godsill, Simon J., Rayner, Peter J.W. with some bespoke improvements on the detection function tracking.</p>
        </blockquote>

    <p>Read more about fluid.transients~ on the <a href='https://learn.flucoma.org/reference/transients'>learn platform</a>.</p>
    <p>fluid.transients~ is part of the Fluid Decomposition Toolkit of the FluCoMa project. For more explanations, learning material, and discussions on its musicianly uses, visit <a href="http://www.flucoma.org/">flucoma.org</a>.</p>
  </discussion>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name='author'>FluCoMa</metadata>
		<metadata name='tag'>Fluid Decomposition</metadata>
		<metadata name='tag'>corpus</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
  <methodlist><method name="reset">
      <arglist />
      <digest>
        Return the object to its original state
      </digest>
      <description>
        Calling <m>reset</m> will change parameter values back to those the object was <i>created</i> with, i.e. any attribute values set in the box will be retained
      </description>
    </method></methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist><attribute name='blocksize' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Block Size
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The size of audio block (in samples) on which the process is operating. This determines the maximum duration (in samples) of a detected transient, which cannot be more than half of <m>blocksize - order</m>. High values are more cpu intensive.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: MAX(<m>order, 100</m>)</li>
    <li>Maximum: <m>4096</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='256' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='clumplength' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Clumping Window Length
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The window size in samples within which anomalous samples will be clumped together to avoid over-detecting in time. This is like setting a minimum transient length.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>0</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='25' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='order' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Order
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The number of previous samples used by the algorithm to create the model of the signal within the <m>blocksize</m> window of analysis. <m>order</m> must be less than <m>blocksize</m>.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: MAX(<m>windowsize, 10</m>)</li>
    <li>Maximum: MIN(<m>blocksize, 200</m>)</li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='20' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='padsize' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Padding
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The size (in samples) of analysis on each side of <m>blocksize</m> used to provide some historical context for analysis, so that each <m>blocksize</m> isn't modelled completely independently of its predecessor.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>0</m></li>
    <li>Maximum: <m>1024</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='128' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='skew' get='1' set='1' type='float64' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Skew
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The nervousness of the bespoke detection function. It ranges from -10 to 10 (it has no units) representing the strength and direction of some nonlinearity applied to the detection signal which controls how peaks are amplified or smoothed before the thresholding. High values increase the sensitivity to small variations.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>-10</m></li>
    <li>Maximum: <m>10</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='0.0' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='threshback' get='1' set='1' type='float64' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Backward Threshold
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The threshold applied to the smoothed backward prediction error for determining an offset. The units are roughly in standard deviations, thus can be considered how &quot;deviant&quot;, or anomalous, the signal must be to be considered transient. When the smoothed error function goes below <m>threshback</m> an offset is identified. As it proceeds backwards in time, it allows tight identification of the end of the anomaly.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>0</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='1.1' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='threshfwd' get='1' set='1' type='float64' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Forward Threshold
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The threshold applied to the smoothed forward prediction error for determining an onset. The units are roughly in standard deviations, thus can be considered how &quot;deviant&quot;, or anomalous, the signal must be to be detected as a transient. It allows tight identification of the start of the anomaly as it proceeds forward.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>0</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='2.0' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='warnings' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Warnings
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>Enable warnings to be issued whenever a parameter value is constrained (e.g. clipped)</p>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='0' /></attributelist></attribute><attribute name='windowsize' get='1' set='1' type='int' size='1'>
        <digest>
              Window Size
        </digest>
        <description>
              <p>The averaging window of the error detection function. It needs smoothing as it is very jittery. The longer the window, the less precise, but the less false positive.</p>
    <p><strong>Constraints</strong></p>
    <ul class="simple">
    <li>Minimum: <m>0</m></li>
    <li>Maximum: <m>order</m></li>
    </ul>

          
        </description><attributelist><attribute name="default" get="1" set="1" type="int" size='1' value='14' /></attributelist></attribute></attributelist>
	<!--RELATED-->
	<seealsolist>
    <seealso name='fluid.buftransients~' />    <seealso name='fluid.sines~' />    <seealso name='fluid.hpss~' /></seealsolist>
</c74object>